<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd">

	<title>Initial configuration</title>
	
	<para>
	After the installation of Package Drone is has to be configured. A database link has
	to be set and a mail server for sending out e-mail.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	As long as there is important configuration missing, most web requests to Package Drone
	will be redirected to the setup view. The setup view should guide you through the whole
	process of setup. The following section describe the process with a bit more detail.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	Also see the wiki page: <link xlink:href="https://github.com/ctron/package-drone/wiki/Setup" />
	</para>
	
	<section xml:id="cfg_admin_user">
	   <title>Login in with admin user</title>
	   
	   <indexterm><primary>Admin user</primary><secondary>Logging in</secondary></indexterm>
	   
	   <para>
	   Initially Package Drone is not configured with any database. Therefore it also
	   has no user accounts available. Instead of falling back to some publicly accessible
	   admin mode oder having some default <code>admin / admin</code> credentials, Package Drone
	   has a special admin user with the user name <code>admin</code> and a random
	   access token. The admin token is either generated on each start of Package Drone or
	   can be provided using a system property or environment variable.  The admin token
	   is also printed out on the console during startup.
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
	   The admin token is written the local file system, in order to allow retrieving it at
	   a later time or for shell scripts. The default location is <filename>~/.drone-admin-token</filename>
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
	   So the first step is to log in using <code>admin</code> and the admin token as password.
	   </para>
	</section>
	
	<section>
	   <title>Database</title>
	   
	   <indexterm><primary>Database</primary></indexterm>
	   
	   <para>
	       Entering the database parameters should be straight forward when you have experience
	       with databases and <acronym>JDBC</acronym>.
	   </para>
	   <para>
	       The default URL schema for MySQL is: <filename>jdbc://mysql/server:port/database</filename>.
	   </para>
	   
	   <note><title>Testing database settings</title>
	       <para>Testing the database settings currently forwards you to a result page. Simply
	       click the <guibutton>Back</guibutton> button of your web broweser to go back.</para>
	   </note>
	   
	   <note><title>Wrong database settings</title>
	       <para>Even if the database settings don't work. They are stored when you
	       press the submit button.</para>
	   </note>
	</section>
	
	<section>
	   <title>Mail server</title>
	   <para>
	       Package Drone needs a mail server for the user registration process. The 
	       mail server must be a server capable of SMTP. So it is not possible to
	       use a <quote>maildrop</quote> setup.
	       
	       <indexterm><primary>Mail server</primary></indexterm>
	       
	   </para>
	</section>
	
	<section>
	   <title>Restore configuration</title>
	   <para>
	       Instead of manually entering all the data, it is also possible to restore a
	       previously generated configuration using the <quote>restore</quote> link, after you
	       logged in as admin. 
	   </para>
	   <para>
	       Also seet <xref linkend="backup_and_restore"/>
	   </para>
	</section>
	
</section>