<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd">

	<title>Web Layer</title>
	
	<para>
	As already mentioned, Package Drone uses Jetty as web server. However it does currently not
	use the OSGi HTTP Service variant. For more information see also:
	<itemizedlist>
	   <listitem><para><link xlink:href="https://wiki.eclipse.org/Jetty/Feature/Jetty_OSGi"/></para></listitem>
	   <listitem><para><link xlink:href="https://www.eclipse.org/jetty/documentation/current/framework-jetty-osgi.html"/></para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
	<para>
	There are two entry points which are currently used. The adapter servlet use the method 
	<link xlink:href="https://wiki.eclipse.org/Jetty/Feature/Jetty_OSGi#Support_for_RFC66">described here</link>.
	and directly provide a <filename>/WEB-INF/web.xml</filename> which defines a servlet.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	The second entry point is used by all web UI elements. A central Jetty Context is registered which
	hosts the <link xlink:href="http://doc.packagedrone.org/javadoc/de/dentrassi/osgi/web/DispatcherServlet.html"><classname>DispatcherServlet</classname></link>,
	which in fact dispatches request to registered
	<link xlink:href="http://doc.packagedrone.org/javadoc/de/dentrassi/osgi/web/Controller.html">web controllers</link>.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	The web dispatching functionality is greatly inspired by the Spring WebMVC framework
	<footnote><para>In fact the WebMVC was used in the beginnging. However, Spring and OSGi don't
	go well together. And although this might sound strange, but Spring is not modular enough
	for OSGi. Spring is modular, but not dynamic. So one Spring is fired up, it can hardly be re-configured
	and does not support services coming and going like OSGi does.</para></footnote>. However it is
	not directly compatible with it, although some class names might look like.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	The dispatcher servlet picks up all web controllers, filters and interceptors and integrates these
	into the main servlet context. It works like a bridge between OSGi services and the JEE parts of Jetty.
	</para>
	
	<variablelist>
	   <varlistentry>
	       <term>Web Controller</term>
	       <listitem>
	           <para>A web controller is a service, registered with OSGi, which provides Java methods
	           which in fact handle incoming web requests. Each method is bound to a URL and request
	           method (GET, POST, …). The method call can have parameters, which are bound to values
	           coming from the URL, the HTTP request or internal processing.</para>
	       </listitem>
	   </varlistentry>
	   <varlistentry>
	       <term>Filter</term>
	       <listitem>
	           <para>
	           These are JEE like Filters, which get registered with OSGi, picked up by the main web context
	           and registered with the dispatching. Filters will be bound to all servlets in the
	           main context.
	           </para>
	       </listitem>
	   </varlistentry>
	   <varlistentry>
	       <term>Interceptors</term>
	       <listitem>
	           <para>These intercept calls to the web controllers only. But they will have access
	           to the values which go in and out of these controllers.</para>
	       </listitem>
	   </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	
	<figure xml:id="figure.web_dispatching">
	<title>Web dispatching</title>
	<mediaobject>
	   <alt>Overview diagram of web dispatching</alt>
	   <imageobject>
	       <imagedata fileref="images/web/web_layer_1.png" format="PNG"/>
	   </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	</figure>
	
	<para>
	As seen in <xref linkend="figure.web_dispatching"/> the Jetty core service takes the Servlet
	from <filename>Bundle A</filename>, defined by the Context path in the <filename>MANIFEST.MF</filename>
	and the servlet definition in the <filename>WEB-INF/web.xml</filename>. And it also takes the
	<classname>Context</classname> service instance registered on the OSGi service bus. In this case
	<filename>Bundle B</filename> directly wired the <quote>Dispatcher Servlet</quote> to the context
	and provides some additional mechanisms order to look up JSP resources in OSGi.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	The Dispatcher servlet however again waits for services registered with OSGi, which have the
	<classname>@Controller</classname> annotation assigned, or are Filters or Interceptors. The default
	dispatcher servlet is registered a the context root path. And, in this case, will forward
	requests for <filename>/c1</filename> to the controller service in <filename>Bundle C</filename>.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	Since also an interceptor in <filename>Bundle D</filename> is registered, the request to <filename>/c1</filename>
	will go through this interceptor. Where the requests to <quote>Servlet A</quote> will not go
	through this interceptor.
	</para>
		
</section>