<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd">

	<title>Introduction</title>
	<para>
	Package Drone is a software artifact repository system. Its main purpose is to
	receive things which come out of a software build process, store them and provide them
	to the next build or deployment step. Also over a longer period of time. 
	</para>
	
	<para>
	There already are a number of artifact formats and repository systems out there. The purpose
	of Package Drone is to bring them all together in a user friendly way. And allow for
	easy extensions of the system. Since there will always be <quote>the next thing</quote>.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	A simple example of what this could be, is a <trademark>Maven</trademark> build process
	which generates <acronym>JAR</acronym>  files. These <acronym>JAR</acronym> files also
	are <trademark>OSGi</trademark> bundles. The Maven build deploys these <acronym>JAR</acronym>
	files to Package Drone using the Maven 2 repository layout and its <acronym>HTTP</acronym> upload
	mechanism. Package Drone can then extract the OSGi and Maven metadata and store everything.
	It can then also provide an Eclipse P2 repository layout so that Eclipse PDE based tools can
	easily access these OSGi bundles directly from Package Drone. Also can users of Bndtools directly
	access the same <trademark>OSGi</trademark> bundles using the <trademark>OSGi</trademark> XML Index
	Repository format, since Package Drone supports both formats.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	The main cause why Package Drone was creates was to work with OSGi bundles. That why Package Drone
	is also called the <quote>OSGi first repository</quote>. However Package Drone can do a lot more, like
	creating APT repositories out of Debian package files, …
	</para>
	
	<para>
	Package Drone is open source and is released under the Eclipse Public License.
	</para>
	
	<section>
	   <title>More information</title>
	   
	   <para>
        More Information about Package Drone can be found on the web.
	   </para>
	   
	   <variablelist>
	   
	       <varlistentry>
	           <term>Homepage</term>
	           <listitem>
	               <para><link xlink:href="http://packagedrone.org" /></para>
	           </listitem>
	       </varlistentry>
	       
	       <varlistentry>
               <term>GitHub Repository</term>
               <listitem>
                   <para><link xlink:href="https://github.com/ctron/package-drone" /></para>
               </listitem>
           </varlistentry>
           
           <varlistentry>
               <term>GitHub Wiki</term>
               <listitem>
                   <para><link xlink:href="https://github.com/ctron/package-drone/wiki" /></para>
               </listitem>
           </varlistentry>
           
           <varlistentry>
               <term>Google+ Page</term>
               <listitem>
                   <para><link xlink:href="https://plus.google.com/+PackagedroneOrg" /></para>
               </listitem>
           </varlistentry>
	   
	   </variablelist>
	   
	</section>
	
	<section>
	   <title>What it is not?</title>
	   
	   <para>
	   Package Drone is open source. So you can change it in any direct you like. However
	   it was created with a few ideas in mind. So there was a plan what it should be able to do,
	   what it could be able to do, and what is if no interest at the moment. The following features
	   are simply not in the scope of people working in Package Drone right now. Of course this
	   may change in the future.
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
	   There are some global, public repository services out there like <quote>Maven Central</quote>
	   or maybe <quote>CPAN</quote>. Package Drone is more a software, a tool for a local development
	   process. And not a global, public super repository service.
	   </para>
	</section>

</chapter>