<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
	>

	<title>Purpose &amp; history</title>
	
	<para>
    One initial idea for Package Drone was to store the BLOBs in the database, together
    with the entity information. Most modern database can store BLOBs efficiently
    and the JDBC API does provide streaming access to BLOBs so that it is not required
    that all BLOBs have to fit into the memory. This would not only simplify the
    implementation, but also would simplify maintenance tasks like backup and restore.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	So much for the theory
	<footnote>
	<para>And please do not say <quote>I told you so</quote>, my colleague already did that.</para>
	</footnote>
	. The real world looks a bit different and both MySQL and
	PostgreSQL do not implement the JDBC streaming correctly, to that in fact the BLOBs
	do get stored in the main memory, at least temporarily. 
	</para>
	
	<para>
	While PostgreSQL can store a BLOB with streaming and only fails when reading the
	BLOB again, MySQL already fails when writing the BLOB and totally explodes when
	reading out the BLOB again. A BLOB gets encoded and parsed when the server
	sends it to the client without any flow control, so the BLOB data is help in encoded
	and decoded form at the same time, which make the 400MB grow to about 1.2GB. 
	</para>
	
	<para>
	In order not to make the file system storage mandatory and support migration to
	the BLOB store from older versions, the store will act as an overlay to the
	already existing database. If future JDBC driver versions will fix these issues,
	it will still be possible to use the <quote>database only</quote> mode. Also could
	it be possible to use other database like Oracle or DB/2 which are reported to work
	much better in this area.
	</para>
	
</section>