<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
	>

	<title>Configuration</title>

    <section>
        <title>Enable</title>
        
        <indexterm>
            <primary>File system store</primary>
            <secondary>Activate</secondary>
        </indexterm>

    <para>
    In order to enable the file system store navigate to <guimenu>System</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Storage</guimenuitem>.
    Enter a non-existing or empty directory into the location entry field and press the <guibutton>Convert</guibutton> button.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    The location entered has to be a non-existing or empty directory in the server where Package Drone is running. The Package Drone
    process user (normally <filename>pdrone</filename>) requires write access in the parent directory if the directory does not
    exists, and write permissions for the directory otherwise.
    </para>
    
    <para>
        <indexterm><primary>File system store</primary><secondary>ID</secondary></indexterm>
    Enabling the store will write this state to database and write out a simple marker file into the directory. Part of this state
    is a unqiue ID which links the database with the file system store. This is used by operations to verify that the database matches
    the file system location.
    </para>

    </section>


    <section>
        <title>Re-locate</title>
        
        <indexterm>
            <primary>File system store</primary>
            <secondary>Re-locate</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        
    <para>
        Sometimes it might be necessary to re-locate the directory of the file store. This can be achieved by shutting down Package Drone,
        moving the full directory structure, starting up Package Drone and using the <quote>re-locate</quote> operation
        from <guimenu>System</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Storage</guimenuitem>. After the file storage has been initialized the
        button will change from <guibutton>Convert</guibutton> to <guibutton>Re-locate</guibutton>.
    </para>
    
    <para>
        <indexterm><primary>File system store</primary><secondary>ID</secondary></indexterm>
        
        Change the location field to point to the correct, new, directory and press <guibutton>Re-locate</guibutton>. The system
        will check if the target directory contains the correct file system store (based on the ID). If not, the operation will
        fail and the new location <emphasis>will not</emphasis> be store in the database. Otherwise the database information
        will be updated with the new storage location and the store is active again.
    </para>
        
    </section>    
    
	
</section>