<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
	xml:id="backup_and_restore"
	>

	<title>Backup and restore</title>
	
	<para>
    The following sections describe the different areas of Package Drone which
    should be backed up and how they can be restored.
	</para>
	
	<section xml:id="sys_settings">
	   <title>System settings</title>
	   
	   <para>
	   These settings contain the information about which database to use and
	   the configuration of the mail server. It <emphasis>does not</emphasis>
	   contain the user information, the channel configuration or anything else
	   from the database.
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
	   Technically this is all configuration information stored in the
	   <acronym>OSGi</acronym> configuration administrator.
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
	   In order to back up these settings go to <guimenu>System</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Backup</guimenuitem>
	   and click on the <guibutton>Export</guibutton> button. This will start the export
	   trigger the download of a ZIP file containing all information. The ZIP file can later
	   be restored. 
	   </para>
	   
	   <para>
	   For restoring the data, again go to <guimenu>System</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Backup</guimenuitem>
	   and select the file to import in the <guilabel>Import configuration</guilabel>
	   section. Start the import process by pressing the <guibutton>Import</guibutton> button.
	   </para>
	   
	   <section xml:id="sys_settings_format">
           <title>File format of system configuration</title>
           
           <para>
           The file is an XML file with the root element <filename>configuration</filename>,
           the <filename>version</filename> attribute must have the value <code>1</code>.
           </para>
           
           <para>
           The children are elements with the name <filename>entry</filename>. Each defining
           an OSGi configuration admin object. Either the <filename>pid</filename> attribute
           or the <filename>factoryPid</filename> attribute has to be set to the service PID
           or the factory PID that this element should be created for.
           </para>
           
           <para>
           Each configuration element contains one or more <filename>property</filename>
           element with the attributes <filename>key</filename>, <filename>type</filename>
           and the value as text content.
           </para>
           
           <para>
           The <filename>type</filename> attribute contains the Java class name which
           of the value.
           </para>
           
           <example>
               <title>Example system settings file</title>
               <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="cfg.xml" parse="text"/></programlisting>
           </example>
       </section>
	   
	</section>
	
	<section>
	   <title>System data</title>
	   
	   <para>
	   All data like artifacts, the artifact binary data, users, deploy keys, all this is
	   stored in the database that is configured for the Package Drone instance.
	   At the moment of writing (Version 0.2.4) there is no backup mechanism for this data.
	   But since it is stored in a MySQL database, you can and should use
	   the mechanisms provided by MySQL for backup up your database.
	   </para>
	   
	   <tip>
	       <title>Database backup</title>
	       <para>
	       If you have a backup of your database, then you have the necessary data
	       you need to re-create an instance of Package Drone.
	       </para>
	   </tip>
	   <para>test</para>
	</section>
	
	
	
</section>